Finding Aid for Bradley R. Cross papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bradley R. Cross papers 1967-1983, 1978-1979
Cross, Bradley R.
3 oversize folders
1.3 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
2013150 Aa 2 UAl UAm
Papers of Bradley Cross, Ann Arbor, Mich. environmental activist and businessman. The bulk of the collection includes material related to the Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association (KHNA) in Pittsfield Township in Ann Arbor, Mich. and its fight to preserve neighborhood natural area by preventing it from commercial development. The legal case filed by KHNA went to the Michigan Supreme Court but was overturned in 1983. This material is dated between 1977 and 1983 and includes correspondence, court documents, maps and plans, position papers, publications, articles and newspaper clippings covering the case, photographs, and audiovisual material. Collection also includes a small number of collected materials related to anti-Vietnam war protests in Michigan and across the country, and Michigan politics, all dated in the 1960s. Included here are publications, campaign signs, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Bradley R. Cross (donor no. 8251 ) in August 2011.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ann Arbor, Mich. native, Bradley Cross received Bachelor's degree in Forestry and Outdoor Recreation from the University of Michigan in 1972. Following graduation he spent three years in Colombia with the Peace Corps and continued environmental and land management consulting in South America while he was enrolled in the University of Michigan Master's program in Wild Land Management. He completed his Master's degree in 1982 but was not able to continue consulting in South America due to political changes that affected environmental policies in those countries. In 1978 Cross opened the Harmony Hollow Bell Works in Ann Arbor. He also served as Membership Chair of Ann Arbor Alliance of Neighborhoods (AAAN)--organization of Ann Arbor neighborhood associations.
In the late 1970s-early 1908s Cross was among members of the Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association (KHNA) in Pittsfield Township fighting to preserve 17.6 acres of undeveloped area lying on the southeast side of the city near the intersection of Packard Road (later Packard Street) and Stone School Road along Gladstone Road (later Gladstone Avenue).
KHNA formed in 1974, for general purpose of preserving what members regarded as the special qualities of the neighborhood, in particular, semi-rural atmosphere of the area: the large number of trees, the dirt roads, the spacious lots, and "mixture of economic groups and occupations." The original purpose of the organization was to fight the installation of storm sewers and paving on Independence, Kimberly, Gladstone, Powell, Columbia, Calumet, and Emerald Roads. Realization of the ultimate disposition of the Straith (later Dion) property would have a significant effect on the character of the neighborhood, and the organization has fought to prevent multiple family development of that property and to establish a natural area there. At the time the KHNA included close to 170 lots with approximately 100 family homes. KHNA proposed to buy land from the realtor, Dion Ventures of Ann Arbor, and donate it to the City of Ann Arbor for use as a nature preserve/park. Donations from neighborhood residents were to pay one half and federal matching funds (administrated by the state of Michigan) for the other half. Over 40 households within the neighborhood collected $27,000 in legally binding pledges toward the purchase of a part of this land for viable nature study area, matching a successful city-sponsored preliminary applications to the State Department of Natural Resources (DNR) for the same amount yielding a total of $54,000. However, in September 1978 the Ann Arbor City Council passed at first reading the rezoning of this land to RIC (single-family housing). Then two weeks later this same Council passed a resolution approving the final application to the DNR for matching funds to purchase the natural area. Thus, the City found itself taking two different and conflicting actions on this piece of property. After a series of KHNA's alternative proposals and negotiations with the developer fell through, KHNA went to court in 1979. In April 1982 the Appeals Court of Michigan reversed the lower courts finding which had been in favor of protecting the natural resources, by way of a permanent injunction under the Michigan Environmental Protection Act. The Court decided that the natural resources were not of statewide significance nor did endangered species inhabit the area so protection was not warranted. KHNA appealed to the Supreme Court of Michigan to reverse decision by the Appeals Court but the case was closed in September 1983 when the Michigan Supreme Court denied motion for reconsideration.
The papers document Cross' work as an environmental activist and businessman. The bulk of the collection includes material related to the Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association (KHNA) in Pittsfield Township in Ann Arbor, Mich. and its fight to preserve neighborhood natural area by preventing it from commercial development. Other material documents antiwar and poitical activism. The collection is organized into two series, Politics and Activism and Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). City Council.; Cross, Bradley R.; Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Land use--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Natural areas--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Neighborhood planning--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Neighborhoods--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pittsfield Charter Township (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Flowers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Insects--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Lakes & ponds--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Neighborhoods--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Parks--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). City Council.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Color slides.; Photographs.
- Politics and activism
  The first series, Politics and activism (0.1 linear feet, 1960s) is a small collection of political publications, leaflets, and brochures, mostly anti-Vietnam War and anti-draft. Included here are Michigan (mostly Ann Arbor) and outside of Michigan materials. Also a number of outsize Michigan election campaign signs, representing candidates of different political parties.
  - Michigan (Box 1)
    (includes photograph)
  - Outside Michigan (Box 1)
  - Campaign signs
- Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association
  The second series, Kimberly Hills Neighborhood Association (1.2 linear feet, 1976-1983) is the heart of the collection. Included here are records of the Association: correspondence, publications, meeting agendas, mailings, histories of the association, area maps and plans, newspaper clippings documenting negotiations and the court case, petitions, statements, and resolutions. Material related to the court case includes correspondence between KHNA and its lawyers, court documents (pleadings, etc.), research material (texts of laws annotated by Cross). Also included material related to other local neighborhood associations, specifically the Ann Arbor Alliance of Neighborhoods (administrative records, publications, correspondence, proposals on behalf of KHNA, etc.) City of Ann Arbor materials include correspondence between KHNA and city officials, memoranda, City Council meeting agendas, texts of addresses to the Council read by KHNA members and supporters during Council meetings, and "Proposed Parks and Open Space Plan" (May 1978). Of interest is folder containing Bradley Cross' handwritten notes, probably taken during meetings, and drafts of letters and memos.
  Audiovisual materials in this series include black-and-white and color photographs and 35 mm slides of the area lying along Gladstone and undeveloped areas—specifically, flora, insects, water reservoirs, as well as neighborhood enlargement works. Also included here is an audiocassette with recording of the January 22, 1979 Ann Arbor City Council meeting.
  - Ann Arbor Alliance of Neighborhoods
    - Administrative records (Box 1)
    - Proposals 1980 (Box 1)
    - Proposals sheet, undated, outsize
    - Publications (Box 1)
    - Slide presentations 1982 (Box 1)
      (script)
    - Working files and notes 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools 1974-1980, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bradley Cross' notes (Box 1)
  - City of Ann Arbor
    - 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Proposed Parks and Open Space Plan: presented to Ann Arbor Mayor and Council by the Mayor's Ad Hoc Committee on Parks and Open Space Plan revision, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Vacant Land Inventory, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 undated (Box 1)
  - Court case
    - Correspondence 1978-1983 (with gaps) (Box 1)
    - Court documents
      - 1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Research (Box 1)
  - History of KHNA (Box 1)
    (includes history of the Stone School site)
  - Maps and plans (Box 1)
  - Maps, outsize
  - Newspaper clippings and articles 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    - Prelude to Housing in Downtown Ann Arbor 1976 (Box 1)
      (student paper)
    - Storm Drainage in Kimberly Hills Subdivision: a Position paper to the Ann Arbor City Council from Administrative Officials 1977 (Box 1)
  - Petitions 1976, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Proposals 1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Proposals, papers by outside parties, 1 folders
    - Analyses of Planning Options and Recommendations: a Study of Transitional and Vacant Land Areas in Ann Arbor, by Gerald Luedtke and Associates 1980 (Box 1)
    - Decision as the Focus in Planning, by Lyle E. Craine, University of Michigan undated (Box 1)
    - Opportunities for a Community Approach in Urban Natural Areas, by Sylvia Taylor and John Lerg, Michigan Department of Natural Resources undated (Box 1)
  - Statements, resolutions 1977, 1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Michigan publications, collected (Box 1)
  - Audiovisual materials
    - Photographs
      - Gladstone undated, 8 photographs black and white (Box 2)
      - Hutzel Pond 1979, 4 photographs color (Box 2)
      - Hutzel Pond-proposed park in rear horizon undated, 4 photographs black and white; photos lined as panorama
      - Kimberly Hills Neighborhood for Enlargements February 1979, 7 photographs color (Box 2)
      - Views of wooded areas undated, 34 photographs black and white (Box 2)
      - Views of wooded areas undated, 4 photographs black and white
    - Slides (35 mm) in 7 boxes (Box 2)
      - Insects and wild flowers, Kimberly Hills Park 1977, 1979, undated, 36 slides color (Box 2)
      - Kimberly Hills, Corridors, Ice 1977, 1979, 27 slides color (Box 2)
      - Kimberly Hills Park 1977, 1980, undated, 12 slides color (Box 2)
      - Kimberly Hills Park 1977, 1979-1980, undated, 37 slides color (Box 2)
      - Kimberly Hills (?) Park, Lake, Ashley September 1977, undated, 20 slides color (Box 2)
      - Straith Property, University of Michigan Campus; 1977, 1979-1980, 35 slides color (Box 2)
      - Unidentified location (Kimberly Hills Park?) 1977, 1979, 1980, 6 slides color (Box 2)
    - Audiocassette
      - Ann Arbor City Council January 22, 1979 (Box 2)